<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/victorpg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/victorpg/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-12-07T19:46:28+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/victorpg/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Landscape power</title><subtitle>Landscape restoration and artificial societies represented as complex systems and interpreted by radical geography</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Introduccion al curso ordenamiento territorial</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/victorpg/updates/2021/11/30/introduccion-ot.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Introduccion al curso ordenamiento territorial" /><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2021-11-30T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/victorpg/updates/2021/11/30/introduccion-ot</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/victorpg/updates/2021/11/30/introduccion-ot.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;auto-organizacion&quot;&gt;Auto-organizacion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observando la estructura espacial de los paisajes donde se realiza actividad humana en el Peru, especialmente en las ciudades, se puede observar un patron particular de crecimiento organico.
El curso&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; busca descifrar las funciones subyacentes que generan y mantienen esa estructura.
La geografia radical provee los instrumentos conceptuales para abordar este estudio incorporando tanto la plataforma espacial descrita como la dimension social operando a traves de los individuos y sus relaciones sociales y economicas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otro enfoque continuamente presente en la interpretacion y la gestion de estos paisajes es el llamado ordenamiento territorial. Este tiene su fundamento primero en la concepcion mecanicista de tratar al paisaje como un objeto inerte que puede ser modificado a partir de su estudio cientifico. Bajo esta premisa se destinan recursos para plasmar ideas a traves de normas que designan usos especificos a porciones del paisaje identificadas por poseer algun atributo o valor especifico dentro de una concepcion generalmente justificada por el llamado bien comun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;independencia.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Source: GoogleEarth (2021)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;De este modo la gestion se hace operativa a traves del concepto de territorio entendido como el espacio donde se ejerce soberania. En los estados modernos este espacio esta delimitado por bordes administrativos dentro de los cuales se implementarian las politicas, estrategias y programas resultantes de esta vision de control restrictivo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volviendo a la observacion inicial del crecimiento organico, se podria discutir los resultados de este enfoque de planificacion, y tambien su validez o pertinencia. Quiza pueda concluirse de manera preliminar que este enfoque se aplica parcialmente y condicionadamente en funcion a los recursos que posee tanto la poblacion como el estado en sus diferentes niveles administrativos. O podria suceder que paralelamente a esta iniciativa de control administrativo opera otra estructura normativa e institucional (de larga data) que sostienen la produccion informal del espacio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La discusion expuesta lineas arriba es una de las posibles aproximaciones al asunto cotidiano de la dinamica espacial que observamos en el paisaje, mediado a traves de instituciones, al cual denominamos territorio. Como tal el territorio es un concepto que permite tanto su comprension como la busqueda de una configuracion que contemple la adopcion de valores que emergen de la sociedad a traves de sus mecanismos e instituciones formalmente e informalmente consensuados.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;desde-el-ordenamiento-hacia-la-gestion-territorial&quot;&gt;Desde el ordenamiento hacia la gestion territorial&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ahora vamos hablar de ordenamiento en su practica como planeamiento espacial. Iremos directo a la critica. El planeamiento es un intento para controlar centralmente aquello que debe hacerse, donde y cuando. Esta vision no siempre toman en cuenta la complejidad de la dinámica territorial, especialmente en casos de transformaciones a gran escala. Incluso, el planeamiento integral a detalle puede limitar la habilidad de gobierno en sus diferentes escalas para abordar nuevas demandas sociales, innovaciones inesperadas y cambios demográficos o económicos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El reconocimiento de la imposibilidad de controlar esos complejos sistemas territoriales, ha devenido en una transicion desde el gobierno coordinador hacia la gobernanza compartida. En el Peru, se marca un hito en esta transicion durante el año 2017 con la creacion del Vice Ministerio de Gobernanza Territorial, como parte de la reorganizacion de la Presidencia del Consejo de Ministros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Ordenamiento Territorial es un curso dictado en la Facultad de Ingenieria Agricola de la Universidad Nacional Agraria La Molina &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="updates" /><summary type="html">Auto-organizacion</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On the new axioms for reading the landscape by Mitchell (2008)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/victorpg/updates/2021/11/30/new-axioms.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On the new axioms for reading the landscape by Mitchell (2008)" /><published>2021-11-30T00:00:00+09:00</published><updated>2021-11-30T00:00:00+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/victorpg/updates/2021/11/30/new-axioms</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/victorpg/updates/2021/11/30/new-axioms.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-review-from-lewis&quot;&gt;A review from Lewis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Original seven axioms (Lewis 1976)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:1&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, provided a reference to interprete landscapes, assuming they are constantly produced by individual interactions within a societal group of changing struggles and paradigms.
Keeping on the original objective, Mitchell (2008)&lt;sup id=&quot;fnref:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-noteref&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn:2&quot; class=&quot;footnote&quot; rel=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; proposed six axioms that are based on empirical findings of his research on the influence that capital circulation have over people role in landscape evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;comparing-both-axioms&quot;&gt;Comparing both axioms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Lewis&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Mitchell&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The landscape is a clue to culture&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;The landscape is produced&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Landscape is a reflection of culture&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Any landscape is or was to functional capitalist creation of value&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Beyond academic interpretation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;No landscape is local&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;History matters&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;History does matter&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Location matters&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Landscape is power&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Physical environment matters&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Landscape is the spatial form that social justice takes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;An obscure meaning can be cleared up by visual evidence&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;-&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;chavimochic.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;source: http://www.chavimochic.gob.pe&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;interpretation&quot;&gt;Interpretation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Michell builds up on Lewis only at the begining, they share the Lefebvrian principle of a socially produced space that allows interpretation from its emergent features. Mitchell continues the argument based on two Radical Geography elements: commodification of space and the search of social justice. These are the main axis of his sequential analysis where his argument is based. Therefore, his contribution goes beyond marxian explanation as it aims to provide a definition of landscape that is operational to social action as a means to counter alienation in the context of production of space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;footnotes&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnotes&quot;&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:1&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://doi.org/10.1080/10464883.1976.10758067 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:1&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li id=&quot;fn:2&quot; role=&quot;doc-endnote&quot;&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4020-5849-3_2 &lt;a href=&quot;#fnref:2&quot; class=&quot;reversefootnote&quot; role=&quot;doc-backlink&quot;&gt;&amp;#8617;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="updates" /><summary type="html">A review from Lewis Original seven axioms (Lewis 1976)1, provided a reference to interprete landscapes, assuming they are constantly produced by individual interactions within a societal group of changing struggles and paradigms. Keeping on the original objective, Mitchell (2008)2 proposed six axioms that are based on empirical findings of his research on the influence that capital circulation have over people role in landscape evolution. Comparing both axioms Lewis Mitchell The landscape is a clue to culture The landscape is produced Landscape is a reflection of culture Any landscape is or was to functional capitalist creation of value Beyond academic interpretation No landscape is local History matters History does matter Location matters Landscape is power Physical environment matters Landscape is the spatial form that social justice takes An obscure meaning can be cleared up by visual evidence - source: http://www.chavimochic.gob.pe Interpretation Michell builds up on Lewis only at the begining, they share the Lefebvrian principle of a socially produced space that allows interpretation from its emergent features. Mitchell continues the argument based on two Radical Geography elements: commodification of space and the search of social justice. These are the main axis of his sequential analysis where his argument is based. Therefore, his contribution goes beyond marxian explanation as it aims to provide a definition of landscape that is operational to social action as a means to counter alienation in the context of production of space. References https://doi.org/10.1080/10464883.1976.10758067 &amp;#8617; https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4020-5849-3_2 &amp;#8617;</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/victorpg/2021/11/22/welcome-to-jekyll.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome!" /><published>2021-11-22T16:52:30+09:00</published><updated>2021-11-22T16:52:30+09:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/victorpg/2021/11/22/welcome-to-jekyll</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/victorpg/2021/11/22/welcome-to-jekyll.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a webpage made to communicate some research I’ve made about the topics of landscape restoration planning and informal urbanization. Also it is going to be posted text and figures regarding contemporary issues related to the economic and politic context where the above mentioned topics are being installed. All the presented themes and discussions are confronted to radical geography theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some brief statement regarding two definitions. First, restoration means ecological restoration of ecosystem services. Second, artificial society is both definition and hypothesis; regarding the former it is the formal computer representation of interacting agents; and the later refers to the actual condition in which individuals are in, performing their agency under deterministic ruling of capitalism; it could be named artificial or second nature, exploration and discussion is open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, landscape concept is developed following J.B. Jackson tradition, this way is employed to disentangle perceived situations about either socio-spatial and ecological processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, this page is hosted in GitHub because it is free and have some code to share.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a webpage made to communicate some research I’ve made about the topics of landscape restoration planning and informal urbanization. Also it is going to be posted text and figures regarding contemporary issues related to the economic and politic context where the above mentioned topics are being installed. All the presented themes and discussions are confronted to radical geography theory. Some brief statement regarding two definitions. First, restoration means ecological restoration of ecosystem services. Second, artificial society is both definition and hypothesis; regarding the former it is the formal computer representation of interacting agents; and the later refers to the actual condition in which individuals are in, performing their agency under deterministic ruling of capitalism; it could be named artificial or second nature, exploration and discussion is open. Thus, landscape concept is developed following J.B. Jackson tradition, this way is employed to disentangle perceived situations about either socio-spatial and ecological processes. Finally, this page is hosted in GitHub because it is free and have some code to share.</summary></entry></feed>